Shand side welcome back to the channel
and today in microservices topic we are
going to do how to build a fall tolerant
microser right so let's start without
wasting any time so when anybody says
that what is fall tolerant microser we
mean to say that a service which
continues to work even when downstream
system fails okay so instead of crashing
or cascading failure it should handle
the failure gracefully. So what in short
you have a system
build up with multiple microservices
even if some of the microservices are
down and your microservices are depend
on them
you should not crash you should handle
the failure gracefully okay then we can
say that it's a fault tolerant microser
okay why it is required you will get
more clarity with this uh example like
why it is required.
So see as in microservices different
services communicate over the network.
We all know this and it's possible that
one service unavailability could bring
down the whole system.
See this example consider that this
system is not fault tolerant. How a one
service can bring down the whole system?
In a normal scenario let's say there
could be multiple microservices which
I'm calling as a client. Right? So let's
say some other client or microservices
is calling order component. Order is
calling product. Products give the
response and order in return gives the
response to the client. This is a normal
flow. Now let's say a buggy code has
been introduced in the product and the
product service becomes too slow. This
products become too slow. Each API is
now taking let's say 60 seconds, right?
60 seconds is too much. In distributed
system, right? Say product service
become too slow and taking 60 seconds to
respond. If proper fall tolerant is not
applied, then a call from order service
will hang for 60 seconds. Now the order
service which is calling the product
service, right? It has to wait for 60
seconds. What if there is a sudden burst
of request coming from client then all
the request
will wait for 60 second. Right? Just see
this example now a sudden burst coming
from a micros service to a order
component order in return calling the
product and product is currently going
too slow. So all the threads are now
waiting.
Okay. All the threads are now waiting.
Now what eventually will happen is
service will run out of thread and start
rejecting the request order.
You know that there is a concept of
thread pool. We have already covered
that in depth. So ultimately when all
the threads are waiting the thread pool
ultimately will get finished. All
threads will get finished and there you
will reach a point when you will start
declining the request and this becomes a
casket failure to all your client and
microservices also. And also one more
thing is even the product component will
not get a normal situation because the
you can say that the situation of a
product service will keep on detering
because more and more load is coming to
the product. So even though issue is at
product
the failure got cascaded to order and
maybe because of order has stopped even
order can get slow order component can
get slow or if its thread is all done it
is start rejecting the request. This
failure can cascade to other components
also. So that is known as cascading
failure. And now you can see that how a
one service can bring down the whole
component whole system.
So that's why we need fall tolerant
that's why we need to build a fall
tolerant microser. So if you are
building a order it need to be fall
tolerant that even if product goes down
or product goes slow I should not
like its failure should not get cascaded
to me and I should not get crashed too.
Okay. So here comes our resilience 4j
framework.
So resilience 4j is a combination of
mechanism like rate limiter, bulkhead,
time limiter, circuit breaker and retry.
So these fives are the combinations or
you can say that the mechanism which
resilience 4j provides which helps to
develop a micros service as fall
tolerant.
And one more thing I would say that we
will go one by one in a recommended
logical ordering. You might say what is
the ordering issue like we can we can
apply anything in in whichever order but
see this is the logical order rate
limiter first then bulkhead then time
limiter then circuit breaker and then
retract right why because there is a
reason like let's say that if you are
applying
right
for example rate limiter should always
be applied before retry now let's say
you are applying first retry and then
rate limiter.
This mechanism you are applying in your
system like this. So does that make
sense to you? Just think what if
rate limiter is that it
whenever an access traffic comes right
it blocks some of the traffic.
Now
if you do the retry mechanism first
means you are unnecessarily wasting your
computation in retrying on those traffic
that ultimately will get blocked by the
rate limiter.
Okay. So there is no point of retrying
those traffic which ultimately get
blocked. So that's why rate limiter
should be first and retire should be
second in this cell. So that's why if
when you are applying all the five
mechanism in your system
logical ordering should be present
that's what there is no hard and fast
rule but this is you can say that uh de
facto which generally should be followed
like this should be the order
okay so let's start with our first
mechanism which is rate limiter very
very important from interview
perspective even when you are building
the services also in product based
system like that's also is very
important. So rate limiter is what it
controls the number of requests allowed
to a micros service in a given time
window. Let's say that in this time
window a particular time window limited
time window let's say 5 second 10 second
whatever how much request can go
through.
So in short it protect our system from
sudden traffic spike like a DOS attack.
Okay. So there are multiple mechanism or
algorithms in rate limiter. Before even
we goes to the implementation. Let's
quickly see what are all the algorithm.
So there are most commonly five
algorithm fixed window counter sliding
log sliding window counter which again
has two flavors token bucket and leaky
bucket. So quickly in 5 10 minutes we
will try to go through each so that uh
when we see the implementation we will
at least get to know what rate limiter
actually does internally.
So fixed window counter let's see the
first fixed window counter.
It is very very simple. It counts how
many request happens in fixed window. If
the count cross the limit then reject
the request. For example, let's say this
is the time period. I am currently
putting into seconds. Uh actually in
coding it could be in nanconds. Okay.
But for simplicity, for understanding
purpose, let's consider that this is a
time period that every request can come
at seconds 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 like this. Now
we have put a limit five that at in a
particular fixed window
if only five requests are allowed. If
more than five comes the rejected. Okay.
So limit is five and window fixed window
size I have given 10 seconds. So now
here if you see this is window one. This
is window one 0 to 10.
This is window two 10 to 20. Okay.
Similarly window 3 would be 20 to 30
like this. Now in each window maximum
count maximum request allowed is only
five. So now let's say one request is
comes at 1 second then here then here
then here then here total five requests.
So all five are allowed because limit is
five for this window and currently it's
within a limit. Now here if you see in
window two 1 2 3 4 5. So these fives are
allowed because limit is five. as soon
as the sixth request comes. So
in this window 10 to 22nd only five are
requests but this sixth is not allowed.
It is crossing the limit. So that's why
it is rejected.
Okay. If any more requests will come
that is also rejected because in this
fixed window already five request has
come. Now in the next window again new
request can come till it don't reach its
limit. limit is five. Very simple,
right? But there is a disadvantage.
Disadvantage is that what if this is
window one, this is window two. What if
all the five requests comes at the last
of this window one
and all the requests in the next window
comes at the start of its window. Now
here if you see in 1 second
10 request has come.
Okay. So that is possible. So if traffic
comes at edge then there is a chance of
sudden spike.
Okay. So there this is one of the
disadvantage in uh you can say that
fixed window counter because it it's
it's a window fixed window and you are
just counting like okay this many
requests are allowed now the request can
comes spread across the window or it can
come like this but if it comes like this
then if you see in 1 second 10 request
your system is able to accept
which it might not be able to handle it.
Okay. Then there is something called
sliding log also again very simple but
with a uh very familiar data structures
which we use sliding window. Right. So
it is very very similar to that one. For
each accepted request it store the exact
timestamp
for each request comes in. It first
check how many request happen in x
seconds window size. So there is a
window slide slider window you can say
that we put that okay 10 seconds 20
seconds whatever so that would be its
size
okay if number of requests reach the
limit it will reject the request we will
see that with an example so here if you
see window size I have put 10 second so
this is my uh the slider size so my
slider size is 10 second and in this
slider size 10 and maximum limit is
five. Maximum five requests I should
accept it not more than that. Now for
each accepted request it stored the
exact time stamp. Now let's say that
first request is coming at this point.
So uh let's say time is started with
1000 0 0. So this is 1000 02 2 seconds.
First request is came
window slider window is still this only.
Okay. Then second request comes at this
10.00.05.
So it is logging the time stamp. Third
request comes at this 10.00007
accepted
because limit is five and only three is
there. And then fourth request come at
10009 9th second. Okay. All four are
accepted. Now let's say that the time
reach till here. Okay. So our window
size is 10. So it has to slide. So now
window slides to 10 seconds.
Okay. So now this is our current window.
Now current window is let's say we are
assuming that time period is in second.
So it is moving second by second. So
earlier window was started from 10 0.
Now it's 1000 01 to 11. So this is my
window size now. So it will only
consider request within this window. So
in this window till now how many
requests are there?
1 2 3 4 till 9 it cames right now let's
say at 11 another request is coming will
it be able to accept it? So currently in
this window only four limit is five. So
yes it will accept it.
Okay. Now let's say that
now window moves again. Now let's say
that time reach till here. So window has
to slide. So window now slides to this
100 02 to 12 10 0 12. Now this is my
window. Now I will check if a request is
coming new request is coming. Does this
window has how many requests? 1 2 3 4 5
already five is there which is already
reached our limit in the window. Now you
are trying to accept a new request which
is in a window. So it will reject it.
Okay. So
very simple right? It just slides
and it just keep track of the accepted
request time stamp.
Now here if you see that one you can say
that one of the disadvantage of this
also that uh one thing is you already
know that it has to manage the time.
Okay which is you require a memory for
that right? more requests means you have
to store their time stamp. Another
problem is that now let's say that
window slides again. Window time reach
till here. Okay. So window has to slide.
So it slide 1 second again. So now our
time is this
03 to 13. Now here if you see that any
time stamp of a request which we
recorded which is now you can say that
out of the window it has to be clean up
right. So that is your extra task which
you have to do because you only need to
consider the time stamp which are
present inside a window.
All the uh time stamp which are beyond
the beyond or before the
window it has to be cleaned up. So that
is disadvantage extra overhead of
cleanup and you need more memory to
store the time frame.
Okay. So very very sliding window kind
of uh solution which is just like based
on time stamp.
Now we have our third is sliding window
counter. Okay. So it has two flavors.
Both flavors are simple. So first flavor
is sliding window counter with sub
windows.
So understand that is that
main window is divided into equal size
sub windows.
Keep track of the number of requests in
each sub window. To decide if requests
need to be rejected or not, it
considered only the active sub windows.
Main window slides over time. Don't
worry about this. Now we will understand
this uh four lines with an example and
it will get uh clearly. So one thing is
we have something called main window. So
let's say window size is 10 second which
ultimately going to slide. Okay. So we
have 10 second window.
Then we have sub window of 2 seconds. So
this is our main window. This yellow one
yellow bucket is our
main window of 10 second. Okay. Then we
have sub windows of 22 2 seconds. So
means this main window is divided into
2 to seconds. Sub windows 0 to2 2 to 4 4
to 6 6 to 8 and 8 to 10. These are sub
windows. Okay. And limit is five. in a
particular window in a particular window
max is five requests we can accept.
Okay. Now what it will do let's see that
how it so till now it is clear right one
we have main window another is the main
window is subdivided into sub windows.
Now for any new request RQ
let's say multiple requests are coming.
So request comes at here limit is five
it is one limit is five only two limit
is five only three limit is five only
four so till now it accept now let's say
that a new request is coming at this 9
second
so it will sum up the request in all
active sub windows all active sub
windows so here the ultimately
window size is main window size is 10
seconds so currently we are at here at
this 9. So its sub window is this one.
This is one sub window 8 to 10. So it
has to count how many number of requests
comes into this window plus
this window because it has to sum up the
sub windows of 10 seconds because main
window is 10 seconds. Okay. So it has to
sum this up.
So ultimately you can say that it all
sub window task is to manage how many
requests coming in their window sub
window. Okay. So ultimately all the sub
windows which are present into the main
window it will just sum it up. Okay. So
here at the 9th second so what are the
sub windows? This one 0 to 2 to 4 4 to 6
to 8 and 8 to 10. So total 0 to 10
seconds. So this is your main window.
Inside this main window, these are the
five sub windows.
Okay. Each sub window is maintaining how
many request comes in their window. Sub
windows. Okay. So we just sum it up. In
0 to 2 second sub window only one
request comes. So it has maintaining
that 2 to 4 only one request came. It is
maintaining that. 4 to 6 only one
request came. 6 to 8 only one and in 8
to 10 currently zero. So how many
requests till now? Four and the limit is
five. So request is allowed at 9.
Okay, it will get more clear. We say
that now let's say time has reached till
this point. Time has reached till this
point. Now window has to move. The main
window has to move. So how much it will
move now? Will it move by 1 1 second?
No, it will here in this it will move by
window size 2 seconds. So 2 second it
will move. Okay. So now you see that
where the sub window also comes into the
so sub window has two part. One is
maintain the count
of requests
within that window. particular window
also is that the main window
slides
or you can say that jump
according to
sub window size. So sub window is 2
second. So when the time reach till this
cross this main window size. So main
window is 10 second. Right? Now time
reach till here. So it has to move. So
how much it will move? It will move by
one window size. So now our size is
this 2 to 12. Earlier it was 0 to 10.
Now it is 2 to 12. Okay. So
here sub windows would be now this one.
These are the active sub windows. 2 to 4
1.
4 to 6 is the second.
6 to 8 is your third. 8 to 10 is your
fourth. 10 to 12 is your fifth. So these
are the five sub windows of 22 to
seconds. Okay. And these are the active.
This one is not active now
because this is now
before the or you can say that the
expired
sub window. Okay. So now when at 11
request is coming so it has to consider
all the active sub window. So this
active one of the sub window is 10 to 12
10 to 12. So 2 to 4 4 to 6 6 to8 8 to 10
10 to 12. So all the sub windows present
into this main sub window main window it
will only consider that and each sub
window maintain how many requests comes
into
that period. Okay. So they will provide
that and ultimately it take outs the
count and it will don't consider the
expired sub window.
Okay. So simple this one. So what are
the disadvantage? First is more complex
than fixed window logic like you have to
maintain sub windows and for each sub
windows you have to maintain the count
of request. Okay. And when the window
slides it has to jump according to the
sub windows. So that is one thing.
Second thing is it it also required more
memory because you have to maintain a
sub window kind of information.
So another flavor of this is which is
little bit simple is sliding window
counter with weighted window.
Okay. So this is actually a combination
of fixed window plus sliding lock
concept. So in fixed window what we have
is let's say fixed window is of 10
second window is of 10 second. So we
have a fixed 0 to 10,
10 to 20, 20 to 30 like this we have
fixed windows. Okay. Like with this is
yellow green. So these are fixed windows
and sliding log. So inside this there we
will have a slider window also of a
similar size 10 seconds. So 10 second 10
second we have a window right slider
window is also 10 second. So this slider
window can slide and when it slide some
part of it might be into the previous
window
or another part would be into the
current window. You can say that. So
here if you see that the window one has
0 to 10 second and another window window
two window one. Window one is 0 to 10
window 2 is 10 to 20. And this slider
window has 80% currently into window one
and 20% into window two. So it is
possible. Okay. So here we have given a
weight.
Now it simplifies our previous uh
where we are doing with sliding window
with sub windows right it simplifies
some task for us that we don't have to
maintain the sub windows. We don't have
to maintain the sub windows like fixed
window we maintain that okay in this
window
0 to 10 0 to 10 how many requests comes
let's say five let's say four whatever
so it just maintain a total request not
sub window type okay so
see this example let's say our limit is
five okay in a in a particular slide
window maximum five request we can
entertain Okay. So currently our time is
0 to 10. Our current time is 0 to 10.
Okay. So now let's say that our window
slider window is also
currently here 0 to 10 all 100%. Slider
window is in the fixed window one. Okay.
Now request is coming at fifth.
All 100% inside this only then 6 7 8 9.
So 1 2 3 4 5 five request comes totally
it is within a limit of five of a slider
window. Okay. So all are accepted.
Okay. So total request count in a fixed
window is five currently because see
here in 0 to 10 it just maintain how
many requests come. So total five total
five request accepted.
Now you will cl get clarified like how
it works. Now let's say time reached
till this point.
Okay. Means time reached into the second
window. Now window two. So this slider
has to move internally. So now slider
has moved till 1 to now the window is
slider window is 1 to 11. Earlier it was
0 to 10. Now it moved by 1 second 1 to
11.
So if you see that the slider 90% is in
window one and currently 10% is in
window two. So it need to see how many
traffic or how many requests are
accepted within this window slider
window. So now just see that it very
very basic mathematics only. So it just
find total request. Total request equals
to
current
fixed window
request count plus. So means whatever in
the current window. This is the current
window, right? This is the current
window.
How many total requests are present into
that? How many total requests we have
accepted currently? Zero plus because
see here we have just moved right
90%. So how many percentage currently we
have here is 90%. Uh 90% of
total request which are entertained into
this window one 0 to 10. So total five
because we are only 90% our window
slider window is into the window one
fixed window one right. So only whatever
the total request we have we only
consider this 90%.
Okay. So let's say it comes out to be a
90% of five is 4.5. So let's say if we
just do seal round off so it would be
considered as a five only. So five is
our limit for a slider window. So we
don't allow a request. So we don't allow
request here. No
simple.
Now you will see that uh disadvantage
also plus with another example here
also. Now the request reach till here.
Okay. Currently slider window at 0 to
11. Right? 0 to 11. Now time reach till
here between 11 to 12. So means slider
has to move. So now let's say slider has
moved. Now it become 2 to 12. This is my
slider window now. So how much it is in
80%. So 80% is in window one
and 20% now is in window 2.
So how many total request
now let's say any new request is coming
should I accept it or reject it? It has
to do first calculate that how many
total requests it has present into this
slider window. So current request count
okay uh you can say that the current
window current window what is the
request count? So currently in 10 to 12
window 2 10 to 12 zero request plus
80% off. So currently 80% of our window
slider window is into the window one
right. So 80% of what are the total
number of request was five. So it just
said 80% of five which is four. So four
is less than
five because five is our limit of a
window slider window. So it will accept
it. It will accept it. But now you see
that this is the disadvantage itself.
Okay. But because now in this slider 2
to 12 how many requests came? 1 2 3 4 5
6. It become more than five. Why?
Because it do not maintain sub windows.
It just compute total request in a fixed
window size. So what if all the requests
present into here at end of the fixed
window. So what happen is our slider
will keep on moving and when the slider
keep on moving its percentage present
into the fixed window keep on reducing
and when this number you are keep on uh
reducing then only this
ultimately will get increased. So
currently here if you see that there is
a chance like 80%.
When you compute for this it gives you
four. It is not accurate info.
So there is a chance that you might
entertain more requests than the limit.
Okay. So 80% of uh total requests. So it
accepted 80% of total request is four.
So it assume that these requests are
spread throughout the window which is
actually not the case. What if all the
requests are end of this and if you are
doing 80% then it might give you four
but that's not the true.
Okay. So this is one of the disadvantage
of the weighted window. I I hope it is
uh clear with this diagram like how the
window slides
uh within a fixed windows.
Then we have token bucket. Token bucket
is very very simplified versions and uh
what happen is we have a kind assume it
like we have a bucket and we placed a
limited tokens inside it. Each request
consume one token.
If there is no token left request is
denied
and there is also a refiller which adds
the token in bucket at regular time
interval.
If bucket capacity is full and cannot
hold more token, token overflow will
happen and token will be rejected. So
understand with this is that this is one
bucket which has capacity of four token.
So 1 2 3 4 four tokens are present.
There is a refiller which task is to add
one token every 6 seconds.
Okay. So now let's say that at 1 2 3 4 5
second five request comes.
So first four because we have four
tokens, right? So first request take one
token accepted accepted. Accepted
accepted. Now all four tokens are used.
Okay. Now fifth request come any token
left. No. So it is rejected.
Now at sixth second a refiller adds one
token. So refiller added one token into
the bucket because we have configured it
that add one token every 6 seconds. So
at 6 second one token is added. Now if
any request comes it will use it and
accept it. Very very simple. So
disadvantage is that a quick burst is
possible if token capacity is not set
properly. What if I have put a token
that in a bucket I have capacity
equals to 1,000. I without doing proper
computation I I give random capacity.
Then means that much token can get
accumulated and what if in a one second
it's a sudden request comes all thousand
so all thousand will get accepted
so there is a chance of bust
traffic okay because whatever the amount
of tokens present that much concurrent
request can be accepted so you have to
consider this token capacity properly
Okay, another is leaky bucket. Leaky
bucket is considered as like requests
are cued and accepted at fixed rate. If
Q is full, incoming request will
overflow. So let's say you have an
incoming request. Okay, bucket or you
can say that a Q which is keep on
accumulating the request. Okay, and the
Q's are accepted at a very constant or
very fixed rate.
So consider this with the flow diagram.
A request comes if Q is full. If this Q
is full then it will send denied and it
will send HTTP 429. Too many requests
can't even accept. If Q has some space
then it will add the request at the end
of the que and from the Q
our system will keep accept the request
in a very constant rate very very
constant rate.
So very simple but disadvantage is your
latency will increase because request
might have to wait in Q for its turn. So
request which is present here it has to
wait for the previous request to finish
it and to be accepted and your queue is
become a bottleneck. So side size should
be set properly. If the size of the
queue is very small you would be denying
lot many requests. If the size is too
big your latency will increase a lot.
Okay. And also memory you need it.
Right.
So these are various algorithms of rate
limiter. I hope with this examples it
will be clear. Just go through this
example one more time slowly and read it
those text like uh the definition which
I have written like this right you read
it you will get clarified little better.
Okay. So we will now let's see that how
it got implemented in spring boot.
So yeah implementation is spring boot.
So first thing first we need resilience
4j dependency.
So I have added this dependency this one
any stable version you can pick. Right.
So this is the dependency I have added
in my pom.xml.
Now rate limiter is just a mechanism
inside uh resilience 4j right. So rate
limiting framework will also comes
inside that also all the classes will
come with this resilience 4j itself.
Now here if you see
first thing is
as usual no change your controller. So
controller is now accepting
like any API which you hit just see that
I have created a service order service.
Okay, this is my order service. So
controller is invoking an endpoint here
right invoke product API. So it is just
invoking invoke product API and inside
this method I am actually doing invoking
the endpoint of a product component.
Okay. So here we have order component.
It is trying to invoke a product
component. Okay. So this is the
controller and here in this I'm just
invoking a service and order service and
there this method nothing much.
Second is I am using a faint client
right we have already covered this in
depth. So I think by this itself you can
collect what is happening. So I have
given one interface for the product
line. Get product by ID. Okay. So this
is my name. I am using service
discovery. This all thing we have
covered already in this playlist. So it
is pretty clear that uh we are using we
we can use any client f client rest
template rest client which we will be
used to communicate between order and
product component.
Okay. So this is also nothing much we
have already seen that. Now here if you
see in the order service the method
which we have written which is like
ultimately invoking this
interface ping client interface right
get product by ID. This is as usual we
are invoking but only this red bucket
this is the something which is deferred.
So here I have annotated this method
with add the rate limiter annotation.
Just give it a name any name to this
rate limiter. Let's say I have given a
product rate limiter because I am
invoking a product API. So I have given
a name product rate limiter and the
fallback method. So now let's say that
multiple request comes and your rate
limiter
denied one of the requests. So this
request which got denied
how it handled? So there is a fallback
method. So we need to provide so it will
ultimately move to that fall back
method. So what so here I have written
that fallback method. So the method name
is rate limited fallback. So rate
limited fallback
inside that you can throw exception or
like how you wanted the exception you
can handle it here. either you can
simply throw the exception here or like
you wanted to handle it you can handle
it according to your business logic.
So only thing which we required is after
dependency whichever the method where
you are actually invoking the end point.
So this is the method where I am
actually invoking the endpoint. You have
already seen this in through fine how to
invoke it. I am invoking product this
but only thing is this is the first
thing which we required for this
annotation. We have to put the rate
limiter annotation on top of that
method. Give it any name to this rate
limiter. Provide a fallback method.
Okay. And this fallback method should
have a signature similar to your this
method original method where you have
written the rate limiter. Return type
should be same. The parameter it accept
a string. So string it should have a
string also. Only thing is apart from
all the similarity apart the next
additional parameter it should have is a
throwable that's all. Apart from that
all the parameter you should match with
your original method
because if it do not match the framework
resilience framework will not be able to
identify your fallback method and it
ultimately moves to the default fallback
method. So resilience uh has some called
rate limiter class rate limiter class.
In that they have something called
default method default fallback method.
So first it will try to look that hey
exact signature fallback is present or
not means return whatever the method you
have written here method name that
method name is present or not it
signature is same or not return type
should be same parameters string so it
also has a string and additionally it
can have just throwable
okay
so that is the first thing which we have
to do very important like
put a rate limiter annotation provide a
fallback method and then in application
doperties
here if you see we have to provide this
configuration so resilience 4j by
default rate limiter uses token bucket.
So it has three properties limit for
period
limit refresh period time duration.
So means your bucket
maximum number of token it has is two.
Maximum number of token it can have is
two. Okay. There is a refiller. There is
a refiller.
After every 10 second it will run and
insert two token.
After
10 second it will keep on adding two
token. But the bucket size is also two.
The same whatever the limit for period
is the same. It is the same bucket size
also. How many token after 10 second?
Two only. Okay. So let's say that no
traffic is come bucket has already two
tokens. If after 10 second another two
token it try to add it will overflow. So
only two is the maximum capacity. If
mode you will try to add it will
overflow and it doesn't get added to
bucket.
Now let's say that
two token were present. Three request
came. So this request one accepted this
token. Request two has used this token.
Now request three 10 second is not yet
over. So new token hasn't been added. So
what request three will done? It will
get rejected. Right? So we pro we can
provide a timeout duration. Hey wait for
1 second before you get rejected. If
after 1 second also there is no new
token get added then you can get
rejected.
Okay. So this is the timeout period we
can define that uh any request which are
not able to find a token instead of
instant rejection we can make it wait
for at least 1 second if in case token
might get present.
Okay. So these all things we have to do.
Now you might be uh thinking that hey
Shange
how this by putting this rate limiter
we have put this rate limiter right
annotation
how this might have working internally
it uses the concept of AOP which in the
spring boot playlist itself I have
discovered in depth very important AOP
so it uses the AOP functionality
only or you can say that the complete
functionality is via AOP only. I won't
go in depth of how AOP works because
that where I have discussed in depth
various point cuts expression right so
everything you will get to know and you
know that we have also discussed how we
can write our own annotation right
we can handle the complete rate limiter
through AOP itself no special framework
code
so what happen is that this rate limiter
like through AOP it intercept the
request.
What it does is it first do your rate
limiting logic.
Okay. So what by default it uses token
based algorithm. Right. So first it will
invoke the class which has token bucket
implementation
and after that from where if it is come
is accepted then it actually proceed.
you remember from AOP we call proceed.
So ultimately invoke the endpoint.
So here uh I will go to this output part
again. Uh but first see that let's say
that this will give you a remind AOP
works. I'm not going in depth but if you
remember from that AOP topic you let's
say I want to write my you say that hey
I want to write my own custom rate
limiter. I don't want to use token
bucket. I don't want to use whatever the
default it is providing. I want to write
my own rate limiter.
So I told you that the rate limiter if
you want different algorithm you have to
handle it through AOP completely. Okay.
So now let's say that first I have to
define an annotation. So I have defined
a custom rate limiter annotation. We
have already seen into this spring boot
playlist how we can define a custom
annotation.
The second part is in the rate AOP I
have told you that we have to write an
expect class right aspect class where we
provide this point cuts.
Okay. So now it is listening to this
annotation and what it has to do once
this annotation is uh called what it has
to do it has to first do a rate limiting
logic. Now whatever the algorithm you
want you can put it ultimate ultimately
call proceed which ultimately invokes
the method right this is your ultimately
method right on which you have put this
annotation at the rate custom rate
limiter
okay so before actually calling this get
product method you can say it first
call this method
uh implement the custom rate limiting
logic and after that it proceed after
that
implement this method.
So this we have already done inside AOP.
So I won't go into depth again. So in
the spring boot playlist you can check
out this AOP one.
So coming back to this now let's say
that with rate limiter
right we have provided a rate limiter
rate limiter name fallback method in
fallback method its signature should be
same as the original method return type
and parameter only thing is throwable
should be extra how you handle it is
totally up to you want to just log it
log it you want to throw exception you
can throw it in the
application.properties properties by
default rate limiter uses u again token
bucket and these are the parameters
which you have set.
Now according to this one we said that
only two tokens are present and after 10
second two more tokens will come and any
request which not able to find a token
should wait for 1 second before it get
rejected. So now here if you see I have
started the service.
Now first I hit instantly hit one. So it
able to call it able to call product
API. Second time I call it able to get
call a product API because it got token.
It got token. The third time I called it
says that rate limit exceeded try later.
So this one it printed out this.
Okay. Then I waited for some time to
over the 10 second so that two more
tokens get added. So after that I hit
again able to hit able to hit. So two
tokens are consumed. Again I hit rate
limit exceeded. Try again later. Then I
waited 10 seconds and then I hit again.
So two times it hit properly. Two tokens
consumed and I try to hit. No rate
limited exceeded.
So this is uh very very simple, right?
So this is what we have done, right? So
the same configuration
just here if you see from postman
hit one time you got it two times.
So see here it waited now. So because
here is some wait happened right that's
why uh so 10 second was over. So now
let's say that let me quickly call 1 2
waited. So after two calls
retry now 10 second is over again 1 2
wait
1 2 wait now let's say I'm quickly
hitting keep on hitting 1 2 3 wait
so till now here if you see two times
token use now hit continuously hit so
rate limit exited because 10 second is
not yet over token is not yet added
now if you hit it it it got involved.
Okay. So you understood right how we can
implement the rate limiter. Okay. And
this name rate limiter name
product rate limiter. This is ultimately
useful in the configuration itself.
Resilience 4j.t rate limiter dot
instance
because there can be many endpoints on
which you have to put this rate limiter.
Okay. So many configuration you have to
put. So this configuration is for this
product rate limiter.
This is product rate limiter. Similarly
you can have for some other component
let's say sales rate limiter. Okay.
I hope this rate limiter concept is
clear and uh next we will see bulkhead
time limiter circuit breaker and retry.
If any doubt uh please feel free to uh
ping in the comment section. We can
discuss further but I would highly
recommend that please go through one
more time. I tried to make sure that I
don't repeat a lot same concept uh
because that's what I get sometime in
comment that uh I go little fast. So if
you think that I am little fast I would
say that try to have a look one more
time and things will get little clear to
you. Okay guys thank you. Bye.